hello I'm your host David Bernard
today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
cat state of subscription apps report
each episode in this series will explore
one crucial metric and share actionable
insights from Top subscription app
operators with me today Brandon gdor
product lead for growth at onx maps on
the podcast I talk with Brandon about
why product is the key to monetization
the psychology of value perception and
the often overlooked impact of Simply
reminding users that they're on the free
plan hey Brandon thanks for joining me
on the podcast today awesome thanks Dave
for having me so I'm really looking
forward to chatting with you I think a
lot of folks in the subscription app
industry don't know about Onyx it's kind
of this uh Sleeping Giant you know not
as many folks in Silicon Valley or just
in Tech Broadley are into hunting and
fishing and outdoor hobbies and so they
just don't realize what a great business
on X is 400 employees millions of users
it's a pretty amazing app and the thing
I wanted to focus on today was
increasing monetization through a
combination of targeted upsells of
Premium features and then I do want to
dig into also subscription tiers let's
get that first one out of the way like
how do you think about targeting users
with that right upsell with the right
feature to improve conversion the most
important thing and this is like true
for any product is like the product
really has to be solved in a problem
first and so you can't like bring
monetization in if there isn't like
value that the user is finding that
they're willing to pay for so I think
like before you can even start to think
about monetization and those elements
like the product Market fit and is this
solving a problem that users you know
deeply care about that they're willing
to pay for is the most important thing I
think it's just important to start there
when you're thinking about monetization
is like the product Market fit and is
this product really solving a problem
and for folks who are struggling with
monetization that really is genuinely
like the first troubleshooting step is
like understand with users is this a
product solving a problem or at least
something people are willing to pay for
so if you build a gimmick like yeah
maybe you're going to monetize a little
bit but there's a lot of product
problems that are Upstream of
monetization problems so I think it's a
fantastic place to start like the next
layer to that is really thinking about
like well what is the monetization
strategy and having kind of a clear line
of sight of that and so you know is it a
trial type app where you're really
trying to drive users into trials to
experience the value of a product or is
it more of a premium approach where
you're just trying to gobble up a bunch
of free users and then convert them over
time and I think like having a a clear
strategy there really informs a lot of
kind of like the following motions and
the metrics you start to optimize and so
those two elements are like what I would
you know make sure that are solid first
before then you start diving into some
of the monetization pieces on Premium
versus free trials I know within Onyx
Maps which is actually kind of unique in
the industry youall have three or four
different products and some of those
products have different strategies
around whether you are just gobbling up
users with a premium strategy or doing
the free trial strategy and so you're
kind of in a unique position working at
a business that itself operates in
multiple models so I'd love your
insights on why freemium or why Onyx
chose it for the different products
what's really unique about our growth
team at Onyx is that we're a horizontal
team and so we actually work across all
these apps that are at different stages
of their life and so the hunt app is the
most mature it's been around the longest
and then the backcountry app is actually
the newer of the apps that we have and
then even within that so you have this
maturity stage of the business and like
the brand awareness and so that
definitely plays a factor into it but
then you also have like well what is the
competitive landscape in these different
areas and in the Hunts space the
competition is rad different than in the
backcountry space where you have a much
more you know I'd say a lot more premium
type products you have more kind of
casual use as far as if you think about
all Trails or or straw for instance
where there's more repeat usage over
time where like hunting is very seasonal
there's specific Seasons when you can go
out and get out in the woods and so that
really plays into the strategy around
how we think about what we're optimizing
for when it comes to monetization so
then where does the rubber meet the road
on converting those users and how do you
think about about that next piece of
monetization first and foremost you be
educating users that what is part of the
paid tier like you know a big I think
learning that we've had is that users
didn't even realize that they were in
the free experience and so sometimes you
just need to be make it like really
obvious that like hey you're part of a
free product here and here's kind of the
value that you're missing behind the pay
wall and so I think education is is a
really it's like the first motion I'd
say and that's education around the paid
tiers but then even around the features
themselves and so some you know a thing
we've been experimenting a lot with is
just like education within the features
trying to communicate the value to the
user what are the outcomes that we can
drive for you as the user by you know
upgrading into one of our paid tiers
that's a a great place to start and so
how are you playing with what features
that users have access to over time and
really trying to understand what is the
particular feature or the user outcome
that is most going to drive users to
want to pull out their wallet and
upgrade into one of the paid tiers and
really experience the value of the
product and so playing with the access
that users have to some of these
features and be willing to experiment
with that cuz I think you can have an
idea or a strategy up front around this
is the basket of things in our pay tier
but I think you'll probably learn a ton
if you start experimenting with that
getting that freemium mix right is what
can really drive a product forward so I
think it's a kind of an undere
experimented with aspect of Premium
subscription apps is actually moving
features in and out of that premium
experience to figure out what's
retaining people and what's actually
driving monetization so fantastic tip
the previous podcast of yours that I
love is the headspace podcast and they
talk about their Journey down this path
and I reference that podcast all the
time because I think it's a really
fascinating case study of how they
played with access over time around
their free user base then when it comes
to monetization like I think the the
third area I'd consider is you know you
have these upsells you're trying to
drive traffic to a particular pay wall
now you're at pay wall you know
optimization I think that's another
really critical area for teams to think
about as far as like the traffic that
you're driving I know in your podcast
you often talk a lot about the pay wall
AB rate and really increasing that and
that's like one of those levers to
really think about is like take premium
for instance like how often are your
free users actually seeing the pay wall
and what are the Motions you can do to
increase the pay wall view rate as well
as then like setting up capability so
that you can run a lot of experiments
you know pending volume but like run a
lot of experiments on that actual pay
wall and really you know optimizing that
if you think about the things that we've
been talking about like education
feature access into the payall and like
what is that end end Journey for the
user and how are you connecting all
those things there's some really
interesting things to experiment and
explore in those themes I actually read
recently that dual linga is getting some
backlash from free users because they
are getting more and more aggressive
about pushing people to the subscription
so how do you think about balancing the
tradeoff of like annoying free users and
potentially causing churn but then hey
it's a business and we do need to
monetize it goes back to the
monetization strategy and I think like
if you are let's say you're you're pling
a freemium strategy and you want to have
this large pool of free users over time
well you're going to think about
different things if it's like really a
trial-based product and we we just want
people to take the trial another thing
that kind of helps distinguish on that
strategy is like the Tam like the
overall opportunity if there's a really
large Tam like you mentioned like dual
lingo you can afford to probably have
you know millions and millions of free
users whereas for some of our products
it's more Niche and so like you know
specifically like in Hunt it's much more
of a trial strategy because that t isn't
like you know everyone out trying to
learn a new language another thing
that's helpful to get aligned as a team
when you're working in this area is like
what are the metrics that we're
optimizing for and then how do we think
about the guard rail metrics of if you
want to be mindful of not pushing people
away how are you thinking about repeat
usage how are you thinking about
uninstalls are you monitoring tickets
into your your customer support team App
Store reviews how do you get that
holistic view of the user experience so
that you are because at the end of day
like I mentioned earlier we had to
communicate a lot to our users that you
actually were in a free product and
sometimes like you have to get in front
of them and it is going to be disrupting
but I think in that case like it was
important to educate our users that
you're actually missing out on all his
value one of the things that I think onx
does really well is that you are are
monetizing those free users well and
then as a more mature product you do now
have multiple tiers how do you
effectively use that to kind of Target
the less expensive tier in certain cases
where maybe you know they're not going
to get the full value but then those
like super die hards you want to make
sure that they can pay you as much as
they're willing to pay my advice you
know for the app Builders out there is
like until you really have a clear user
need around an additional tier when is
the opportunity to bring it then because
I think like by introducing it too early
it introduces all sorts of complexity
into the business and it ends up being I
think more work than it's actually worth
when you have a really clear hey this is
our paid tier you have different
durations of it and that becomes a
really easy choice for the user to
understand around like what are they
paying for and so what really works well
with the hunt tiering package is that
like it's baked in a a user problem
around the access that you get across
the country so we have a premium product
which is one state we also have a
premium two-state package and then we
have our our top tier which is Elite
which is access to all 50 states plus
Canada and Mexico I think from the users
perspective it's really easy for them
you know coming in onboarding seeing the
pay wall they can grock like okay I I
can understand the value or the
difference between these different tiers
whereas if it's just kind of a basket of
features in the different tiers and
you've kind of sliced them dice it by
like an idea that you had I think it's
really tough for the user to understand
what's the difference between these two
in the value within them in that Elite
tier I know y'all have created some
Partnerships and added a lot of value
like discounts to other brands and and
things like that that are actually
really attractive and again something
that onx can do as a much more mature
product as a bigger company but this the
kind of thing I think a lot of people
can be thinking about when you think
about how do we add value well adding
value isn't just that next feature you
build you can add value through
Partnerships and through so many other
ways so tell me how on does that this is
a great Point around how we think about
like the elite tier and there's like
there's been a constant effort around
how do we round out the feature set and
the value that we could provide our
users within our highest paying tier and
so you know our Elite price is $100
which is a lot to ask for in in the app
store which is funny because I kind of
don't think it is in a way because I
think you'll still have a ton of room to
grow monetization because I know a lot
of hunters here in the Texas area and I
mean you'll spend thousands if not tens
of thousands of dollars a year on this
hobby so yes if for an app it's
expensive broadly probably not exactly
and I think it's in the context of the
user and like what they're spending for
their hobby so you're totally right but
I think in the mindset of like paying
you're in the App Store and you're
paying like $100 is a lot at the time
and so a part of that strategy is been
like how do we broaden the feature set
capabilities in our Elite package and
one component of that is the
Partnerships with Brands and so as an
Elite member you get a a discount or
some sort of like extra value with these
partners that we have and to your point
these hobbies are really expensive and
sometimes the deals that you can get on
these Partners can make up the value of
the app in a single purchase so you're
exactly right do those Partnerships also
plan to growth at all like when you
partner with an outdoor clothing line
like camo and all that kind of stuff um
do they help promote the app yeah
exactly to give you like an example um
in the hunt product we we partner with
first light and so first light is an
outdoor or apparel company and so
there's a lot of kind of cross promotion
that happens between those two brands
that um you know first like being a
Premiere outdoor apparel company when
people see Onyx next to that um that
Association happens there and so we do a
lot of kind of cross collaboration with
these Brands to help Drive growth what a
great win-win where you're able to
deliver value to your users and and
create those extra incentives for the
premium tier but then you're also
driving some extra growth and brand
awareness through these Partnerships any
other specific examples around targeted
upsells that you think the audience
would be interested in one of the areas
where we probably learned the most
around these Target upsells and kind of
to your previous question around like
how do we find that balance of not being
intrusive in the experiences well one is
like how do you bake it natively into
the experience and like anytime you can
naturely have that upgrade flow or that
CTA is part of like the natural user
experience like that's where we've seen
success and as far as the user
experience because you're not it's not
like a jarring Interruption but I'd say
another like really critical part of
this is like the strategy is like the
who and when and so who are the cohorts
that you're targeting and being really
thoughtful around the specific cohorts
and being able to Target on kind of
different vectors but then the when and
the context and like how you think about
the context of the user did they
recently interact with a particular
feature how long have they've been with
the product and I'd say it takes both of
those you need The Who and and the
context to really be working together to
be most impactful here I think the last
part of that is kind of how do you carry
that through into the experience of the
upgrade and the context of the value
that you're communicating to the user
when you've gotten them to kind of start
that journey of the upgrade path and I
think all Trails does a really nice job
with this with some of their upsells
where for instance like if you're a free
user and you interact with the 3D part
of their map now the pay wall actually
has this great highlight video of 3D and
it kind of it's giving you the value
prop of 3D and so it kind of goes back
to that end then user experience I was
referencing earlier is like how are you
having that continuity through the
entire upgrade is where you'll see the
most impact this has been so much fun
Brandon I think there's so many tips
folks can take away anything you wanted
to share as we're wrapping up is the
team hiring or anything else you wanted
to share uh no I mean first off thank
you David so much for having me on the
podcast like I'm a huge fan of the work
that you all are doing and I've learned
a ton from the different guests that
you've had so I really appreciate
everything you do there I mean last
thing I'd say is like you know onx these
are purpose built products for folks
that are trying to get out in the
outdoors and so whether you're a
Backcountry skier a hiker an off-roader
or you're curious about hunting you know
check out some of our apps they're
pretty amazing products and and yeah
awesome thanks so much for joining me
today this is so much fun thanks
Dam thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private community